Guide to the Montana Legislative Assembly (7th: 1901) records 1899-1901
Montana Historical Society
Montana Legislative Assembly (7th: 1901) records
1899-1901
Montana Historical Society Archives
LR 7
Montana. Legislative Assembly.
.4 linear feet of shelf space
Records (1899-1901) of the Montana 7th Legislative Assembly consist of Joint special committee to Investigate the Insane Asylum; minutes and reports of special joint committees; minutes and reports of House standing committees; and miscellany, including correspondence, petitions, and subject files on contested elections. [OVERSIZE MATERIAL: Box #1]
The Montana State Legislature is made up of two chambers, the Senate and the House of Representatives. The Constitution of Montana limits the size of the Senate to no fewer than 40 and no more than 50 members and the size of the House of Representatives to no fewer than 80 and no more than 100 members. Each house is responsible for choosing its officers, creating committees and establishing its own rules. The Montana Legislature meets for 90 days every odd numbered year, beginning the first Monday in January, or the following Wednesday if the first Monday is New Years Day. The first State Legislature convened on November 23, 1889, fifteen days after Montana became a state. Each following Legislature has been numbered sequentially.
The 7th Montana Legislature met from January 7th to March 7th, 1901. The leaders of the Senate were Frank Higgins (D-President), and G.H. Stanton (D-President Pro Tempore). The leaders of the House were Frank Corbett (D-Speaker), and John Baker (D-Speaker Pro Tempore).
Sources:The Constitution of the State of Montana as adopted by the Constitutional Convention March 22, 1972, and as ratified by the people, June 6, 1972, referendum no. 68, "A GUIDE TO THE MONTANA LEGISLATURE," The Montana Legislature,; “Montana Legislative Leadership 1889 – Present”.
Records (1899-1901) of the Montana 7th Legislative Assembly consist of Joint special committee to Investigate the Insane Asylum; minutes and reports of special joint committees; minutes and reports of House standing committees; and miscellany, including correspondence, petitions (re support of and opposition to repeal of anti-gambling law; support of H.B. 65 making railroads liable for damages and injuries sustained by employees; opposing sale of remaining U.S. public land and supporting construction of reservoirs for arid lands; supporting meat and milk inspection; supporting funding for a bridge across Yellowstone River in Custer County; supporting legislation prohibiting the company store system; opposing hunting licenses; supporting changes in duck hunting season; supporting practice of osteopathy; supporting an additional deputy for Silver Bow County; supporting the creation of a State Board of Health; opposing use of streams as waste courses for the carrying off of coal slack and other refuse; supporting division of Rock Creek Valley from Granite County and its annexation into Missoula County; and opposing separation of Flathead Indian Reservation from Missoula County and its annexation into Flathead County), and subject files on contested elections. [OVERSIZE MATERIAL: Box #1]
The collection is organized into five series, House and Senate Special Joint Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically), House of Representatives Standing Committee Minutes and Reports (arranged alphabetically), General Correspondence (arranged alphabetically), Subject Files (arranged alphabetically), and Miscellany (arranged alphabetically).
Oversize Material: Box #1 is restricted. Patient files are confidential and privileged (M.C.A. 53-21-166), but may be used for research under the administrative rule adopted by the Department of Public Health and Human Services. Consult an archivist for details and a copy of the Application to Conduct Research form.
Acquisition information available upon request
OVERSIZE MATERIAL: Box #1
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Bills, Legislative--Montana.; Legislative bodies--Montana--Committees.
Montana--Politics and government.
Montana.; Government and Politics.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- House and Senate Special Joint Committee Reports
  - Special Committee to Investigate the Insane Asylum, 1901 February (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Special Committee to Investigate the Insane Asylum ("Report Showing Name and Number of Employees, Etc..;" and "[Monthly] Report of the Contractors for the Insane Asylum," includes name of patient, date, admitted, form of insanity, change since last report, chance of recovery, county seat from, and days cared for) OVERSIZE MATERIAL: Box #1 [Restricted], 1901 January (Oversizebox OVFD)
- House of Representatives Standing Committee Minutes and Reports
  - Appropriations Committee (Includes Joint House Appropriations and Senate State Institutions and Public Buildings Committees), 1901 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Judiciary Committee (re S.B, 87, the disqualification of Judges), 1901 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
- General Correspondence
  - To Appropriations Committee (includes requests for appropriations from various agencies; a report by the Montana Agricultural Experiment Station on Irrigation Investigations; and draft legislation, 1899 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
- Subject Files
  - Medals for Returning Montana Veterans of the Spanish-American War, 1899 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
- Miscellany
  - Contested Elections: T.F. Pollard vs. C.H. Gregory (re Carbon County House Seat; includes transcript of testimony), 1900 December (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Contested Elections: Charles Jackway vs. Michael Geary (re Deer Lodge County House Seat), 1900 December (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - Contested Elections: Charles H. Williams vs. John Madden (re Deer Lodge County House Seat), 1900 December (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - Contested Elections: John C. English vs. John E. McDonnell (re Deer Lodge County House Seat), 1900 December (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - Contested Elections: M.J. Fitzpatrick vs. Thomas McTague (re Deer Lodge County House Seat), 1900 December (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - Contested Elections: William R. Allen vs. John R. Toole (re Deer Lodge County House Seat), 1900 December (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - Contested Elections: H.M. Brooks vs. E.J. Anderson (re Meagher County Senate Seat), 1900 December (Box-folder 1 / 12)
  - Contested Elections: H.M. Brooks vs. Nathan Godfrey (re Meagher County Senate Seat), 1900 December (Box-folder 1 / 13)
  - Contested Elections: T.W. Flowers vs. George T. Baggs (re Ravalli County House Seat), 1900 December (Box-folder 1 / 14)
  - Contested Elections: John A. Landram vs. Aaron Connor (re Ravalli County House Seat), 1900 December (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - Petitions (re support of and opposition to repeal of anti-gambling law), 1900-1901 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
  - Petitions (re support of H.B. 65 making railroads liable for damages and injuries sustained by employees; opposing sale of remaining U.S. public land and supporting construction of reservoirs for arid lands; supporting meat and milk inspection; supporting funding for a bridge across Yellowstone River in Custer County; supporting legislation prohibiting the company store system; opposing hunting licenses; supporting changes in duck hunting season; supporting practice of osteopathy; supporting an additional deputy for Silver Bow County; supporting the creation of a State Board of Health; opposing use of streams as waste courses for the carrying off of coal slack and other refuse; supporting division of Rock Creek Valley from Granite County and its annexation into Missoula County; and opposing separation of Flathead Indian Reservation from Missoula County and its annexation into Flathead County), 1900-1901 (Box-folder 1 / 17)